<history title="1900">
	<period>
		<name>1800–1809</name>
		<text>1800–1809</text>
		<events>
			<event>
				<time>1800.0</time>
				<text>The company of surgeons are awarded their royal charter and became the royal college of surgeons of england.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1800.0</time>
				<text>The inception of the second great awakening for the united states.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1800.0</time>
				<text>Alessandro volta invents the first chemical battery</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1801.0</time>
				<text>Giuseppe piazzi discovers the dwarf planet ceres.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1801.0</time>
				<text>Thomas jefferson elected president of the united states by the united states house of representatives, following a tie in the electoral college (united states)</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1801.0</time>
				<text>The kingdom of great britain and the kingdom of ireland merge to form the united kingdom.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1801.0</time>
				<text>Ranjit singh crowned as king of punjab.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1801.0</time>
				<text>Napoleon signs the concordat of 1801 with the pope.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1801.0</time>
				<text>Cairo falls to the british.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1801.0</time>
				<text>Assassination of tsar paul i of russia.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1801.0</time>
				<text>British defeat french at the second battle of abukir</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1801.0</time>
				<text>Barbary war between the united states and the barbary states of north africa</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1802.0</time>
				<text>Treaty of amiens between france and the united kingdom ends the war of the second coalition.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1802.0</time>
				<text>Ludwig van beethoven performs his moonlight sonata for the first time.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1803.0</time>
				<text>William symington demonstrates his charlotte dundas, the "first practical steamboat".</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1803.0</time>
				<text>The united states more than doubles in size when it buys out france's territorial claims in north america via the louisiana purchase. this begins the u.s.'s westward expansion to the pacific referred to as its manifest destiny which involves annexing and conquering land from mexico, britain, and native americans.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1803.0</time>
				<text>The wahhabis of the first saudi state capture mecca and medina.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1803.0</time>
				<text>War breaks out between britain and france; this is considered by some to be the beginning of the napoleonic wars.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1804.0</time>
				<text>Haiti gains independence from france and becomes the first black republic.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1804.0</time>
				<text>Austrian empire founded by francis i.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1804.0</time>
				<text>Napoleon crowns himself emperor of the french.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1804.0</time>
				<text>World population reaches 1 billion.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1804.0</time>
				<text>First steam locomotive begins operation.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1804.0</time>
				<text>Morphine first isolated.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1804.0</time>
				<text>Fulani jihad in nigeria.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1804.0</time>
				<text>Serbian revolution erupts against the ottoman rule. suzerainty of serbia recognized in 1817.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1805.0</time>
				<text>The battle of trafalgar eliminates the french and spanish naval fleets and allows for british dominance of the seas, a major factor for the success of the british empire later in the century.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1805.0</time>
				<text>Napoleon decisively defeats a austrian-russian army at the battle of austerlitz.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1805.0</time>
				<text>Muhammad ali modernizes egypt.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1806.0</time>
				<text>Holy roman empire dissolved as a consequence of the treaty of pressburg.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1806.0</time>
				<text>Cape colony becomes part of the british empire.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1807.0</time>
				<text>Britain declares the slave trade illegal.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1808.0</time>
				<text>Beethoven performs his fifth symphony</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1808.0</time>
				<text>Russia conquers finland from sweden in the finnish war.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1808.0</time>
				<text>Spanish guerrillas fight in the peninsular war.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1809.0</time>
				<text>Napoleon strips the teutonic knights of their last holdings in bad mergentheim.</text>
			</event>
		</events>
	</period>
	<period>
		<name>1810s</name>
		<text>1810s</text>
		<events>
			<event>
				<time>1810.0</time>
				<text>The university of berlin is founded. among its students and faculty are hegel, marx, and bismarck. the german university reform proves to be so successful that its model is copied around the world (see history of european research universities).</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1810.0</time>
				<text>The grito de dolores begins the mexican war of independence.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1810.0</time>
				<text>Most of the latin american colonies free themselves from the spanish and portuguese empires after the latin american wars of independence.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1812.0</time>
				<text>The french invasion of russia is a turning point in the napoleonic wars.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1812.0</time>
				<text>War of 1812 between the united states and the united kingdom</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1813.0</time>
				<text>Jane austen publishes pride and prejudice</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1814.0</time>
				<text>Napoleon abdicates and is exiled to elba.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1813.0</time>
				<text>The contest between the british empire and imperial russia for control of central asia is referred to as the great game.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1814.0</time>
				<text>Anglo-nepalese war between nepal(gurkha empire) and british empire.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1815.0</time>
				<text>The congress of vienna redraws the european map. the concert of europe attempts to preserve this settlement, but it fails to stem the tide of liberalism and nationalism that sweeps over the continent.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1815.0</time>
				<text>Napoleon escapes exile and begins the hundred days before finally being defeated at the battle of waterloo and exiled to st helena. his defeat brings a conclusion to the napoleonic wars and marks the beginning of a pax britannica which lasts until 1870.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1816.0</time>
				<text>Year without a summer: unusually cold conditions wreak havoc throughout the northern hemisphere, likely caused by the 1815 explosion of mount tambora.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1816.0</time>
				<text>Independence of argentina</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1816.0</time>
				<text>Shaka's zulu kingdom becomes the largest in southern africa.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1817.0</time>
				<text>Principality of serbia becomes suzerain from the ottoman empire. officially independent in 1867.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1817.0</time>
				<text>First seminole war begins in florida.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1817.0</time>
				<text>Russia commences its conquest of the caucasus.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1818.0</time>
				<text>Mary shelley writes frankenstein</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1818.0</time>
				<text>Independence of chile</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1819.0</time>
				<text>Peterloo massacre in england.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1819.0</time>
				<text>The modern city of singapore is established by the british east india company.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1819.0</time>
				<text>Théodore géricault paints his masterpiece the raft of the medusa, and exhibits it in the french salon of 1819 at the louvre.</text>
			</event>
		</events>
	</period>
	<period>
		<name>1820s</name>
		<text>1820s</text>
		<events>
			<event>
				<time>1820.0</time>
				<text>Missouri compromise</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1820.0</time>
				<text>Regency period ends in the united kingdom</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1820.0</time>
				<text>Discovery of antarctica</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1820.0</time>
				<text>Liberia founded by the american colonization society for freed american slaves.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1820.0</time>
				<text>Dissolution of the maratha empire.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1820.0</time>
				<text>At least 5000 mexicans die in apache raids, and 100 settlements are destroyed.[8]</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1821.0</time>
				<text>Mexico gains independence from spain with the treaty of córdoba.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1821.0</time>
				<text>Peru declares its independence from spain.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1821.0</time>
				<text>Navarino massacre</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1822.0</time>
				<text>First mexican empire, as mexico's first post-independent government, ruled by emperor agustín i of mexico.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1821.0</time>
				<text>Greece becomes the first country to break away from the ottoman empire after the greek war of independence.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1822.0</time>
				<text>Prince pedro of portugal proclaimed the brazilian independence on september 7. on december 1, he was crowned as emperor dom pedro i of brazil.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1823.0</time>
				<text>The british empire annexed burma (now also called myanmar) after three anglo-burmese wars.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1823.0</time>
				<text>Monroe doctrine declared by us president james monroe.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1824.0</time>
				<text>Premiere of beethoven's ninth symphony.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1825.0</time>
				<text>Erie canal opened connecting the great lakes to the atlantic ocean.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1825.0</time>
				<text>First isolation of aluminum.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1825.0</time>
				<text>Independence of bolivia.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1825.0</time>
				<text>The stockton and darlington railway, the first public railway in the world, is opened.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1825.0</time>
				<text>The argentina-brazil war results in the independence of uruguay.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1826.0</time>
				<text>Samuel morey patents the internal combustion engine.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1826.0</time>
				<text>After the final russo-persian war, the persian empire took back territory lost to russia from the previous war.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1827.0</time>
				<text>Death of william blake, ludwig van beethoven</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1828.0</time>
				<text>Black war in tasmania leads to the near extinction of the tasmanian aborigines</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1829.0</time>
				<text>Johann wolfgang von goethe's faust premieres.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1829.0</time>
				<text>First electric motor built.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1829.0</time>
				<text>Sir robert peel founds the metropolitan police service, the first modern police force.</text>
			</event>
		</events>
	</period>
	<period>
		<name>1830s</name>
		<text>1830s</text>
		<events>
			<event>
				<time>1830.0</time>
				<text>The church of jesus christ of latter day saints is established on april 6, 1830.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1830.0</time>
				<text>July revolution in france.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1830.0</time>
				<text>The belgian revolution in the united kingdom of the netherlands led to the creation of belgium.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1830.0</time>
				<text>Greater colombia dissolved and the nations of colombia (including modern-day panama), ecuador, and venezuela took its place.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1830.0</time>
				<text>830 november uprising in poland against russia.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1831.0</time>
				<text>France invades and occupies algeria.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1831.0</time>
				<text>Great bosnian uprising against ottoman rule occurs.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1831.0</time>
				<text>Charles darwin's journey on the hms beagle.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1831.0</time>
				<text>November uprising ends with crushing defeat for poland in the battle of warsaw.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1831.0</time>
				<text>Egyptian–ottoman war.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1832.0</time>
				<text>The british parliament passes the great reform act.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1833.0</time>
				<text>Slavery abolition act bans slavery throughout the british empire.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1833.0</time>
				<text>Carlist wars in spain.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1834.0</time>
				<text>The german customs union is formed.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1834.0</time>
				<text>Spanish inquisition officially ends.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1834.0</time>
				<text>Britain amends the poor law demanding that any paupers requesting assistance must go to a workhouse.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1834.0</time>
				<text>Imam shamil's rebellion in russian-occupied caucasus.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1835.0</time>
				<text>The texas revolution in mexico resulted in the short-lived republic of texas.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1836.0</time>
				<text>Battle of the alamo ends with defeat for texan separatists.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1836.0</time>
				<text>Battle of san jacinto leads to the capture of general santa anna.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1837.0</time>
				<text>Telegraphy patented.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1837.0</time>
				<text>Charles dickens publishes oliver twist</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1837.0</time>
				<text>Rebellions of 1837 in canada.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1837.0</time>
				<text>Queen victoria's reign is considered the apex of the british empire and is referred to as the victorian era.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1838.0</time>
				<text>By this time, 46,000 native americans have been forcibly relocated in the trail of tears.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1838.0</time>
				<text>Civil war in the federal republic of central america led to the foundings of guatemala, el salvador, honduras, nicaragua, and costa rica.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1839.0</time>
				<text>Kingdom of belgium declared.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1839.0</time>
				<text>Uruguayan civil war</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1839.0</time>
				<text>After two opium wars, france, the united kingdom, the united states and russia gained many concessions from china resulting in the decline of the qing dynasty.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1839.0</time>
				<text>Anglo-afghan wars lead to stalemate and the establishment of the durand line</text>
			</event>
		</events>
	</period>
	<period>
		<name>1840s</name>
		<text>1840s</text>
		<events>
			<event>
				<time>1840.0</time>
				<text>New zealand is founded, as the treaty of waitangi is signed by the māori and british.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1841.0</time>
				<text>The word "dinosaur" is coined by richard owen</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1842.0</time>
				<text>Treaty of nanking cedes hong kong to the british.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1842.0</time>
				<text>Anaesthesia used for the first time.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1843.0</time>
				<text>The first wagon train sets out from missouri.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1843.0</time>
				<text>Short stories a christmas carol and the tell-tale heart published.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1844.0</time>
				<text>Persian prophet the báb announces his revelation on may 23, founding bábísm. he announced to the world of the coming of "he whom god shall make manifest". he is considered the forerunner of bahá'u'lláh, the founder of the bahá'í faith.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1844.0</time>
				<text>First publicly funded telegraph line in the world—between baltimore and washington—sends demonstration message on may 24, ushering in the age of the telegraph. this message read "what hath god wrought?" (bible, numbers 23:23)</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1844.0</time>
				<text>Millerite movement awaits the second advent of jesus christ on october 22. christ's non-appearance becomes known as the great disappointment.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1844.0</time>
				<text>The great auk is rendered extinct.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1844.0</time>
				<text>Dominican war of independence from haiti.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1845.0</time>
				<text>Unification of the kingdom of tonga under tāufaʻāhau (king george tupou i)</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1845.0</time>
				<text>First anglo-sikh war</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1845.0</time>
				<text>The new zealand land wars</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1845.0</time>
				<text>The irish potato famine leads to the irish diaspora.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1846.0</time>
				<text>The mexican-american war leads to mexico's cession of much of the modern-day southwestern united states.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1846.0</time>
				<text>Mormon migration to utah.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1847.0</time>
				<text>The brontë sisters publish jane eyre, wuthering heights and agnes grey</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1847.0</time>
				<text>The caste war of yucatán.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1848.0</time>
				<text>Second anglo-sikh war</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1848.0</time>
				<text>The communist manifesto published.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1848.0</time>
				<text>Revolutions of 1848 in europe</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1848.0</time>
				<text>Seneca falls convention is the first women's rights convention in the united states and leads to the battle for suffrage and women's legal rights.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1848.0</time>
				<text>California gold rush</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1849.0</time>
				<text>The first boatloads of gold prospectors arrive in california, giving them the nickname 49ers.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1849.0</time>
				<text>The safety pin and the gas mask are invented</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1849.0</time>
				<text>Earliest recorded air raid, as austria employs 200 balloons to deliver ordinance against venice.</text>
			</event>
		</events>
	</period>
	<period>
		<name>1850s</name>
		<text>1850s</text>
		<events>
			<event>
				<time>1850.0</time>
				<text>The little ice age ends around this time.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1850.0</time>
				<text>Taiping rebellion is the bloodiest conflict of the century, leading to the deaths of 20 million people.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1851.0</time>
				<text>The great exhibition in london was the world's first international expo or world's fair.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1851.0</time>
				<text>Louis napoleon assumes power in france in a coup.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1851.0</time>
				<text>The platine war ends and the empire of brazil has the hegemony over south america.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1851.0</time>
				<text>Victorian gold rush in australia</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1852.0</time>
				<text>Frederick douglass delivers his speech "the meaning of july fourth for the negro" in rochester, new york.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1853.0</time>
				<text>United states commodore matthew c. perry threatens the japanese capital edo with gunships, demanding that they agree to open trade.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1853.0</time>
				<text>Crimean war between france, the united kingdom, the ottoman empire and russia</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1854.0</time>
				<text>Battle of balaclava and the charge of the light brigade.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1854.0</time>
				<text>The convention of kanagawa formally ends japan's policy of isolation.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1854.0</time>
				<text>Siege of sevastapol; city falls to british forces.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1855.0</time>
				<text>Bessemer process enables steel to be mass produced.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1856.0</time>
				<text>World's first oil refinery in romania</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1856.0</time>
				<text>Neanderthal man first identified.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1857.0</time>
				<text>Indian rebellion of 1857. the british empire assumes control of india from the east india company.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1858.0</time>
				<text>Invention of the phonautograph, the first true device for recording sound.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1859.0</time>
				<text>Charles darwin publishes on the origin of species.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1859.0</time>
				<text>Suez canal is constructed.</text>
			</event>
		</events>
	</period>
	<period>
		<name>1860s</name>
		<text>1860s</text>
		<events>
			<event>
				<time>1860.0</time>
				<text>Guiseppe garibaldi launches the expedition of the thousand</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1860.0</time>
				<text>The pony express started.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1861.0</time>
				<text>American civil war between the union and seceding confederacy</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1861.0</time>
				<text>Russia abolishes serfdom.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1861.0</time>
				<text>French intervention in mexico and the creation of the second mexican empire, ruled by maximilian i of mexico and his consort carlota of mexico.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1862.0</time>
				<text>The pony express ended.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1862.0</time>
				<text>French gain first foothold in southeast asia</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1862.0</time>
				<text>Muslim rebellion in northwest china.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1863.0</time>
				<text>Bahá'u'lláh declares his station as "he whom god shall make manifest". this date is celebrated in the bahá'í faith as the festival of ridván.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1863.0</time>
				<text>Formation of the international red cross is followed by the adoption of the first geneva convention in 1864.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1863.0</time>
				<text>First section of the london underground opens.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1863.0</time>
				<text>France annexes cambodia.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1863.0</time>
				<text>Polish uprising against the russian empire.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1864.0</time>
				<text>The chincha islands war was an attempt by spain to regain its south american colonies.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1864.0</time>
				<text>The war of the triple alliance ends paraguayan ambitions for expansion and destroys much of the paraguayan population.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1865.0</time>
				<text>Reconstruction in the united states; slavery is banned in the united states by the thirteenth amendment to the united states constitution.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1865.0</time>
				<text>865-april 9, 1865 robert e. lee surrenders the army of northern virginia (26,765 troops) to ulysses s. grant at appomattox courthouse, virginia, effectively ending the american civil war.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1865.0</time>
				<text>865-april 14, 1865, united states president abraham lincoln is assassinated while attending a performance at ford's theater, washington, d.c.. he dies approximately nine hours after being shot on april 15, 1865.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1865.0</time>
				<text>Gregor mendel formulates his laws of inheritance</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1866.0</time>
				<text>Successful transatlantic telegraph cable follows an earlier attempt in 1858.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1866.0</time>
				<text>Austro-prussian war results in the dissolution of the german confederation and the creation of the north german confederation and the austrian-hungarian dual monarchy.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1866.0</time>
				<text>Famine in finland.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1866.0</time>
				<text>After the meiji restoration, japan embarks on a program of rapid modernization.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1867.0</time>
				<text>The united states purchases alaska from russia.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1867.0</time>
				<text>Canadian confederation formed.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1867.0</time>
				<text>The principality of serbia passes a constitution which defines its independence from the ottoman empire. international recognition followed in 1878.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1868.0</time>
				<text>868; the expatriation act is approved by congress, guaranteeing u.s. citizens the right to expatriate. coupled with the 14th amendment to the u.s. constitution approved only one day later, the expatriation act allows u.s. citizens to renounce federal citizenship in order to regain constitutional rights ceded by u.s. citizens as defined by the 14th amendment.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1868.0</time>
				<text>The 14th amendment to the u.s. constitution is approved.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1868.0</time>
				<text>Cro-magnon man first identified.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1868.0</time>
				<text>Ten years' war between cuba and spain</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1869.0</time>
				<text>First transcontinental railroad completed in united states on may 10.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1869.0</time>
				<text>The suez canal opens linking the mediterranean to the red sea.</text>
			</event>
		</events>
	</period>
	<period>
		<name>1870s</name>
		<text>1870s</text>
		<events>
			<event>
				<time>1870.0</time>
				<text>The franco-prussian war results in the unifications of germany and italy, the collapse of the second french empire, the breakdown of pax britannica, and the emergence of a new imperialism.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1871.0</time>
				<text>Famine in persia is believed to have caused the death of 2 million.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1871.0</time>
				<text>Second industrial revolution</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1870.0</time>
				<text>Long depression in western europe and north america</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1871.0</time>
				<text>The feudal system is dismantled in japan.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1871.0</time>
				<text>Henry morton stanley meets dr. david livingstone near lake tanganyika.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1872.0</time>
				<text>Yellowstone national park, the first national park, is created.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1872.0</time>
				<text>The first recognised international soccer match, between england and scotland, is played.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1873.0</time>
				<text>Maxwell's a treatise on electricity and magnetism published.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1873.0</time>
				<text>The samurai class is abolished in japan.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1873.0</time>
				<text>Blue jeans and barbed wire are invented.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1874.0</time>
				<text>The société anonyme coopérative des artistes peintres, sculpteurs, and graveurs, better known today as the impressionists organize and present their first public group exhibition at the paris studio of the photographer nadar.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1874.0</time>
				<text>The home rule movement is established in ireland.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1874.0</time>
				<text>The british east india company is dissolved.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1874.0</time>
				<text>First republic in spain.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1875.0</time>
				<text>Hms challenger surveys the deepest point in the earth's oceans, the challenger deep</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1875.0</time>
				<text>26 million indians perish in india due to famine.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1876.0</time>
				<text>Bulgarians instigate the april uprising against ottoman rule.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1876.0</time>
				<text>Richard wagner's ring cycle is first performed in its entirety.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1876.0</time>
				<text>Queen victoria becomes empress of india.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1876.0</time>
				<text>Battle of the little bighorn leads to the death of general custer and victory for the alliance of lakota, cheyenne and arapaho</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1876.0</time>
				<text>13 million chinese die of famine in northern china.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1876.0</time>
				<text>The massive expansion in population, territory, industry and wealth in the united states is referred to as the gilded age.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1877.0</time>
				<text>Great railroad strike in the united states may have been the world's first nationwide labor strike.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1877.0</time>
				<text>Crazy horse surrenders and is later killed</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1877.0</time>
				<text>Asaph hall discovers the moons of mars</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1877.0</time>
				<text>Thomas edison invents the phonograph</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1877.0</time>
				<text>Following the russo-turkish war, the treaty of berlin recognizes formal independence of the principality of serbia, montenegro and romania. bulgaria becomes autonomous.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1878.0</time>
				<text>First commercial telephone exchange in new haven, connecticut.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1879.0</time>
				<text>Anglo-zulu war in south africa.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1879.0</time>
				<text>Thomas edison tests his first light bulb</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1879.0</time>
				<text>Little war against spanish rule in cuba leads to rebel defeat.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1879.0</time>
				<text>Chile battles with peru and bolivia over andean territory in the war of the pacific.</text>
			</event>
		</events>
	</period>
	<period>
		<name>1880s</name>
		<text>1880s</text>
		<events>
			<event>
				<time>1880.0</time>
				<text>The first boer war.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1880.0</time>
				<text>The brsjak revolt ends in present-day macedonia, the ottomans defeat the macedonian rebels, after 6 months of battles.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1881.0</time>
				<text>Tsar alexander ii is assassinated</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1881.0</time>
				<text>Wave of pogroms begins in the russian empire.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1881.0</time>
				<text>Gunfight at the o.k. corral. sitting bull surrenders.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1881.0</time>
				<text>First electrical power plant and grid in godalming, britain.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1881.0</time>
				<text>The mahdist war in sudan.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1882.0</time>
				<text>The british invasion and subsequent occupation of egypt</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1883.0</time>
				<text>Krakatoa volcano explosion, one of the largest in modern history.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1883.0</time>
				<text>The quagga is rendered extinct.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1883.0</time>
				<text>Robert lewis stevenson's treasure island is published</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1884.0</time>
				<text>Siege of khartoum</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1884.0</time>
				<text>Germany gains control of camaroon</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1884.0</time>
				<text>Mark twain publishes the adventures of huckleberry finn.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1884.0</time>
				<text>The berlin conference signals the start of the european "scramble for africa". attending nations also agree to ban trade in slaves.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1884.0</time>
				<text>The sino-french war led to the formation of french indochina.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1885.0</time>
				<text>King leopold ii of belgium establishes the congo free state as a personal fiefdom</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1885.0</time>
				<text>Britain establishes a protectorate over bechuanaland (modern botswana)</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1885.0</time>
				<text>"the strange case of dr. jekyll and mr. hyde" by robert louis stevenson is published.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1885.0</time>
				<text>Singer begins production of the 'vibrating shuttle' which would become the model t of sewing machines.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1886.0</time>
				<text>Burma is presented to queen victoria as a birthday gift</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1886.0</time>
				<text>Karl benz sells the first commercial automobile</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1886.0</time>
				<text>Construction of the statue of liberty</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1886.0</time>
				<text>Russian-circassian war ended with the defeat and the exile of many circassians. imam shamil defeated.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1887.0</time>
				<text>The british empire takes over balochistan</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1887.0</time>
				<text>Sir arthur conan doyle publishes his first sherlock holmes story, a study in scarlet.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1888.0</time>
				<text>Jack the ripper murders occur in whitechapel, london</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1888.0</time>
				<text>Slavery banned in brazil.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1889.0</time>
				<text>Eiffel tower is inaugurated in paris.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1889.0</time>
				<text>Mirza ghulam ahmad establishes the ahmadi muslim community.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1889.0</time>
				<text>End of the brazilian empire and the beginning of the brazilian republic</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1889.0</time>
				<text>Vincent van gogh paints starry night</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1889.0</time>
				<text>Aspirin patented.</text>
			</event>
		</events>
	</period>
	<period>
		<name>1890s</name>
		<text>1890s</text>
		<events>
			<event>
				<time>1890.0</time>
				<text>The wounded knee massacre was the last battle in the american indian wars. this event represents the end of the american old west.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1890.0</time>
				<text>Italy annexes eritrea.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1890.0</time>
				<text>Independence of luxembourg.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1890.0</time>
				<text>Death of vincent van gogh.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1890.0</time>
				<text>The cardboard box is invented.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1891.0</time>
				<text>Chilean civil war.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1892.0</time>
				<text>Basketball is invented.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1892.0</time>
				<text>The world's columbian exposition was held in chicago celebrating the 400th anniversary of christopher columbus's arrival in the new world.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1892.0</time>
				<text>Fingerprinting is officially adopted for the first time</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1892.0</time>
				<text>Tchaikovsky's nutcracker suite premières in st petersberg</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1893.0</time>
				<text>Us forces overthrow the government of hawaii</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1893.0</time>
				<text>New zealand becomes the first country to enact women's suffrage</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1894.0</time>
				<text>First commercial film release by jean aimé le roy</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1894.0</time>
				<text>First gramophone record</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1894.0</time>
				<text>France and the russian empire form a military alliance</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1894.0</time>
				<text>After the first sino-japanese war, china cedes taiwan to japan and grants japan a free hand in korea.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1895.0</time>
				<text>Volleyball is invented</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1895.0</time>
				<text>Trial of oscar wilde and premiere of his play the importance of being earnest</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1895.0</time>
				<text>French troops capture antananarivo in madagascar</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1895.0</time>
				<text>Wilhelm röntgen identifies x-rays</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1894.0</time>
				<text>Dreyfuss affair</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1895.0</time>
				<text>Ethiopia defeats italy in the first italo–ethiopian war.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1895.0</time>
				<text>Cuban war for independence results in cuban independence from spain</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1896.0</time>
				<text>Olympic games revived in athens.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1896.0</time>
				<text>Philippine revolution ends declaring philippines free from spanish rule.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1896.0</time>
				<text>Ethiopia defeated italy at the battle of adwa.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1896.0</time>
				<text>Klondike gold rush in canada.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1896.0</time>
				<text>Henri becquerel discovers radioactivity; jj thompson identifies the electron, though not by name.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1897.0</time>
				<text>Gojong, or emperor gwangmu, proclaims the short-lived korean empire: lasts until 1910.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1897.0</time>
				<text>Benin expedition of 1897 loots and burns benin</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1897.0</time>
				<text>Greco-turkish war.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1898.0</time>
				<text>The united states gains control of cuba, puerto rico, and the philippines after the spanish-american war.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1898.0</time>
				<text>Empress dowager cixi of china engineers a coup d'état, marking the end of the hundred days' reform; the guangxu emperor is arrested.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1898.0</time>
				<text>H. g. wells publishes the war of the worlds</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1898.0</time>
				<text>The boxer rebellion in china is suppressed by an eight-nation alliance.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1898.0</time>
				<text>The one thousand days war in colombia breaks out between the "liberales" and "conservadores", culminating with the loss of panama in 1903.</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1899.0</time>
				<text>Second boer war begins (-1902); philippine-american war begins (-1913).</text>
			</event>
			<event>
				<time>1899.0</time>
				<text>Indian famine begins.</text>
			</event>
		</events>
	</period>
</history>
